<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Your Blog</title><link>https://YOURUSER.github.io/blog</link><description>Things you talk about</description><pubDate>Thu, 02 Jan 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><lastBuildDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 04:07:39 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>marmite</generator><item><title>The story of the sneaky zeros</title><link>https://YOURUSER.github.io/blog/the-story-of-the-sneaky-zeros.html</link><category>blog</category><category>null values</category><category>zero-values</category><guid>https://YOURUSER.github.io/blog/the-story-of-the-sneaky-zeros.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 02 Jan 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><source url="https://YOURUSER.github.io/blog">index</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>For my master’s project, I was using a dataset which provided me with a large collection of LLM output text, alongside a numerical label indicating how significant of a hallucination was contained in the text (the consistency rating) for some of the entries. It was a neatly organised table (or so it appeared), with columns dedicated to all sorts of interesting metrics. Everything seemed fine at first glance. But first glances can apparently be very deceptive!</p>
<p>The goal was simple: calculate the average consistency rating for each category and draw some profound insights. Sounds easy, right? I wrote the SQL query with the confidence of someone who had yet to be betrayed by their own dataset. Seconds later, the results appeared, and something looked... off.</p>
<p>One category had an average consistency rating so low that it felt like the LLM had been purposely trying to spread disinformation. “Surely that can’t be right,” I thought. But who was I to argue with the numbers?</p>
<h1><a href="#the-suspicion-sets-in" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="the-suspicion-sets-in"></a>The suspicion sets in</h1>
<p>After double-checking my query and confirming I had the right column, the confusion began to set in. Not wanting to accept defeat, I began looking through the dataset thoroughly. Row by row, everything was looking perfect, until I spotted them: the zeros. Now you may be thinking &quot;Well zeros are normal, right? They mean no consistency.&quot; But as I kept scrolling, something clicked. Why were some entries NULL and others explictly zero? And why were entries which seemed to be factually correct being marked with a zero consistency rating? What kind of prank was this? Who thought it would be a good idea to mix NULLs and zeros like that and set out to ruin my computation?</p>
<h1><a href="#the-aftermath" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="the-aftermath"></a>The aftermath</h1>
<p>For those unfamiliar with the subtle art of SQL averages, here's the twist: NULL values are ignored in calculations, while zeros are not. So when my dataset tossed in a few stealthy zeros alongside the NULLs, it dragged the average consistency rating straight into the abyss. Sadly, since there were some legitimate zero-consistency examples in the database, I had to abandon the dataset in favour of a smaller, but more functional, dataset.</p>
<h1><a href="#lessons-learned" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="lessons-learned"></a>Lessons learned</h1>
<ol>
<li><strong>Never blindly trust your data.</strong> It can be out to get you!</li>
<li><strong>Zeros and NULLs are not the same.</strong> They may look innocent, but one will quietly step aside while the other ruins your calculations.</li>
<li><strong>Manual inspection can be very valuable.</strong> Even a quick skim-through of the dataset can sometimes reveal important information about your dataset.</li>
</ol>
<h1><a href="#data-snippet" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="data-snippet"></a>Data Snippet</h1>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Text</th>
<th>Consistency</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Usain Bolt will compete at the relay championship on May 2 and 3 ...</td>
<td>1.67</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Serena Williams beat Sara Errani 4-6 7-6 ...</td>
<td>2.67</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Buckingham Palace guard slipped on manhole cover in front of hundreds ...</td>
<td>0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Brazilian coach Ze Maria was fired on Wednesday after poor run ...</td>
<td>2.33</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Chipotle has decided to tap into the $70 billion food delivery market ...</td>
<td>NULL</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>The statement &quot;Buckingham Palace guard slipped on manhole cover...&quot; is in fact consistent (should be NULL)! See: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cqmG5JWLRag">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cqmG5JWLRag</a></p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Bad naming is bad</title><link>https://YOURUSER.github.io/blog/bad-naming-is-bad.html</link><category>welcome</category><category>blog</category><category>marmite</category><category>example</category><category>test</category><category>fancycompanyname</category><guid>https://YOURUSER.github.io/blog/bad-naming-is-bad.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><source url="https://YOURUSER.github.io/blog">index</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[<h1><a href="#give-a-dog-a-bad-name" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="give-a-dog-a-bad-name"></a>Give a dog a bad name</h1>
<p>This is a test post.</p>
<p>We at Fancy Company treat our data very badly.</p>
<p>For example, we never give names to variables</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>x</th>
<th>y</th>
<th>z</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>1</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>3</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>But what are x y and z?</p>
<h1><a href="#and-then-forget-it" aria-hidden="true" class="anchor" id="and-then-forget-it"></a>and then forget it</h1>
<p>don't know, don't remember it</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>